Thomas Paine Papers ca.1692-1921 Mss.B.P165
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Paine Material, 1775-1808
  - AMS Accidental Reconciliation, From the Castle in the Air to the little Corner of the World", n.d.; 2 items (7p.); Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    Paine's undated poem and the newspaper that it appeared in, "The New-York Weekly Museum. No. 21.-vol. XLX. New-York, Saturday, July 4, 1807."
  - MS copy. Age of Reason., See bound volumes; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - MsCy of Common Sense, n.d.; 35p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    This "2:Edition" was supposedly copied by Paine for Samuel Clay Harvey, J.P. of Lodge Hill, Kent, England. Enclosed note, however, maintains that this manuscript is "not in Thomas Paine's handwriting, although there is a certain similarity..."
  - Ams, n.d.; 4p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - AMS. Cape of Good Hope, n.d.; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    "Cape of Good Hope"
  - AMS. General Wolfe, n.d.; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    "General Wolfe"
- Series II. Miscellaneous Material, 1692-1921
  Consists of correspondence and manuscripts about Paine, as well as other unrelated material. The Dr. Samuel Adams correspondence are also included
  - ADS to Thomas Holme, 1624-1695, 1692 July 6; 1p.; Markham, William, 1635 -1704 (Box 2)
    Legal document Colonial Governer Markham to Thomas Holme, Surveyor General of Pennsylvania, regarding a land purchase.
  - AM, ca. 1730; 2p.; Unknown (Box 2)
    About an armorial design for Sailor Buttet. In French.
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1775 January 17; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Robert R. Livinston, 1746-1813, 1776 January 25; 1p.; Hallett, Joseph (Box 2)
    About erecting a "Foundry."
  - ALS to Colonel Donop, 1776 December 22; 1p.; Cadwalader, John, 1742-1786 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1777 August 18; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1779 September 29; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    About the death of Paine's wife.
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1779 October 25; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ADS to David Rittenhouse, 1732-1796, 1780 March 18; 1p.; Bayard, John Bubenheim, 1738-1807 (Box 2)
    Order to pay Thomas Paine.
  - ALS to Joseph Hart, 1780 June 29; 1p.; Moore, William (Box 2)
    About apprehending a "Woman" accused of "general disaffection to the American Cause."
  - PrDS to David Rittenhouse, 1732-1796, 1780 September 23; 2p.; Bayard, John Bubenheim, 1738-1807 (Box 2)
    Order to pay Thomas Paine "for his Wages for One Hundred Fourteen Days Service in the Assembly; As Clerk.. ." On reverse: Receipts to David Rittenhouse from Thomas Paine, 1780, October 28-1781, January 19.
  - PrDS to Benjamin Franklin or the Minister Plenipotentiary of the United States, 1780 October 3; 1p.; Hopkinson, Thomas (Box 2)
    Order to pay Thomas and Benjamin Harwood "One Hundred Mexian Dollars, or Five Hundred Livres Tournois."
  - ALS to Peter Molini, 1781 September 11; 1p.; Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797 (Box 2)
    About Molini's "delicate and troublesome commission."
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1782 May 3; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1782 October 31; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1782 November 22; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1783 January 27; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1783 February 12; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1784 August 9; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1784 September 26; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1785 March 22; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1786 February 8; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1786 September 20; 6p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1786 October 1; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1787 July 26 29; 4p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1787 November 4; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1788 March 14; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1788 April 14; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1788 July 13; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - Extract of ALS, 1790 September 14; 2p.; Author unknown (Box 2)
    "Extrait Dela Deliberation del. Assemblee Coloniale..."
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1792 February 26 March 24; 9p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Fabre d'Eglantine, ca.1792 October; 2 items (2p.); Domergue, Urbain, 1745-1810 (Box 2)
    Expressing support for Charles de Pougens for dutyship in the National Convention. (In French)
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1793 April 17; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - LS to the Members composing the committee of Public Safety, Paris, 1794 November 1; 3p.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831 (Box 2)
    An appeal to the committee to release Paine from Prison.
  - ADSCy of Affadavit sent to Stanley, 1795 February 7; 2p.; Abbott, John (Box 2)
    Copy of an original affadavit swearing that five of his schoolboys signed the Petition for the sum of one penny each.
  - ALS to Henry Dundas, 1742-1811, 1795 February 7; 1p.; Ackers, James, 1756?-1827 (Box 2)
  - ADSCy, 1795 February 7; 2p.; Harrison, Samuel (Box 2)
    Another copy of an affadavit swearing that schoolboys were coerced into signing "the Petition" at the Bull's Head in Manchester.
  - ADS to Obediah Clough, 1795 October 9; 2p.; Foster, Abiel, 1735-1806 (Box 2)
    Receipt to Clough.
  - Ms, ca. 1796; 28p.; Author unknown (Box 2)
    An anonymous manuscript on the English financial system of the period. Handwritten on the cover: "...a reply to Thomas Paine's Decline and Fall of the English System of Finance c 1796"
  - AL to unknown, 1797 June 19; 3p.; Foster, Abiel, 1735-1806 (Box 2)
  - ADS, 1798 February 19; 1p.; Author unknown (Box 2)
    Legal document concerning Monsieur Cout L'Aine`
  - ALS to Ez. Williams, 1798 March 17; 2p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 2)
  - ALS to J. M. West, 1802 January 9; 1p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 2)
  - ADS and PrDS, 1804 September 26- 1811 August 15; 8 items; Permanent Bridge Company (Box 2)
    Business and financial records.
  - ALS to Dennis O'Bryen, 1805 January 11; 1p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 2)
  - ALS to (Dennis?) O'Bryen, 1805 December 31; 3p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 2)
    About politics and also a request for a dog.
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1806 November 29; 2p.; Sickels, John H. (Box 3)
    Lottery business.
  - ALS to Dennis O'Bryen, 1807 June 10; 2p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 3)
    About an apparent falling-out that O'Bryan has had with a Mr. Philips.
  - ALS to Stephen Jacob, 1755-1817, 1808 February 11; 3p.; Barlow, Joel, 1754-1812 (Box 3)
  - MsS, 1809 August 31; 1p.; Bonneville, Nicolas de, 1760-1828 (Box 3)
    Discharge of debt.
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1813 January 21; 2p.; Gilbert, William W. (Box 3)
  - ADS to Raphael Marshall, 1815 October 19; 1p.; Cook, Moses (Box 3)
    Promissory note to Marshall.
  - ADS, 1818 June 16; 1p.; Kern, John (Box 3)
    Receipt
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 February 20; 1p.; Mumford, Gordon (Box 3)
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 March 17; 1p.; Mumford, Gordon (Box 3)
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 March 18; 1p.; Allen, M. (Box 3)
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 April 20; 1p.; Mumford, Gordon (Box 3)
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 May 1; 1p.; Mumford, Gordon (Box 3)
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 May 13; Mumford, Gordon (Box 3)
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 May 27; 3p.; Cooper, Charles (Box 3)
    Lottery business
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 June 16; 2p.; Burrall, Jonathan, 1759-1805 (Box 3)
    Receipt for lottery tickets signed by Burrall.
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1819 July 16; 1p.; Mumford, Gordon (Box 3)
  - PDS to unknown, 1820 February 25; 1p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 3)
    Solicitation for financial support of Cobbett's candidacy for "the City of Coventry."
  - ALS to Archibald McIntire, 1820 August 28; 1p.; Mumford, Gordon (Box 3)
  - Archibald McIntire, 1820 October 13; 1p.; Mumford, Gordon (Box 3)
  - ALS to Benjamin Wilson, 1821 January 12; 1p.; Deavis, Henry (Box 3)
    Sent to conservation. 8/29/01
  - ALS to Benjamin Silliman, 1779-1864, 1822 April 4; 2p.; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858 (Box 3)
  - ALS "To the King", 1824 December 27; 1p.; Carlile, Richard, 1790-1843 (Box 3)
  - ALS to Mr. Swan, 1830 November 17; 1p.; Carlile, Richard, 1790-1843 (Box 3)
    About the discontinuation of the Choral Society meetings.
  - ALS to unknown, 1830 December 23; 1p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 3)
  - ALS to George Miller, 1794-1856, 1831 January 16; 1p.; Carlile, Richard, 1790-1843 (Box 3)
  - ALS to Robert Balfour, 1740?-1818, 1832 January 25; 1p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 3)
    Brief itinerary.
  - ALS to Hugh Craig, 1833 December 7; 1p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 3)
  - ALS to unknown, 1834 September 18; 2p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 3)
    Under Cobbett's signature: "The foregoing address was read by Mr. Cobbett on the balcony of Mr. Dodd's House in Sackville Street on Thursday the 18th of September 1834, to at least thirty thousand citizens. P.O.H."
  - ALS to Major William Henry French, 1815-1881, 1837 May 5; 1p.; Somerset, Lord Fitzroy James Henry, 1788-1855 (Box 3)
    Regarding an appointment.
  - ALS to Francis Ormond Jonathan Smith, 1806-1876, 1846 August 1; 1p.; Evans, George Henry, 1805-1856 (Box 3)
  - ALS to John Orcutt, 1847 August 9; 2p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    About Paine's last words.
  - Fragment of ALS to unknown, 1850 April 13; 2p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    A very self-congratulatory letter about Thorburn's important role in assisting with the yellow fever crisis and also introducing horticulture to the country.
  - ALSCy to Grant Thorburn, 1773-1863, 1851 June 7; 1p.; Bronson, P. (Box 3)
  - AMS, 1851 August 12; 13p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "Sixty years reminiscences in the life of Grant Thorburn"
  - AM, 1852 January; 5p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "Men and Manners in South Carolina, written for the _____, by Laurie Todd, To my Abolition friends in New York..."
  - AN, 1854 October 8; 1p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    Memorandum
  - AM, 1855 August; 6p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "Slate Nails, August 1855, Grant Thorburn, [alias Laurie Todd]"
  - ALS to P.C. Manning, 1857 October 17; 1p.; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860 (Box 3)
  - ALS to James, Parton, 1822-1891, 1877 November 1; 3p.; Ingersoll, Robert Green, 1833-1899 (Box 3)
  - ALS to Miss J. H. Johnston, 1891 January 22; 1p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
  - ANS to J. H. Johnston, 1895[?] October 5; postcard; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
  - Fragment of ALS to Moncure Daniel Conway, 1832-1907, 1895 November 28; 1p.; Unknown (Box 3)
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1896 December 18; 6p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    Regarding Paine portraits that Johnston has in his possession.
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1896 December 23; 2p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    Paine's portrait.
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1897 January 13; 4p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    More about the Paine portraits.
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1897 April 10; 2p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    Debate about the actual Paine portrait painter.
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1897 June 16; 2p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    About getting a good price for the Paine portrait.
  - ANS to J. H. Johnston, 1897 September 19; postcard; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1897 October 7; 4p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    Conway warns Johnston that the Paine portrait is not so valuable after all.
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1897 October 12; postcard; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    More debate over the portrait.
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1897 October 21; 3p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    Conway urges Johnston to produce a bill for the work he's had done on the portrait.
  - ALS to J. H. Johnston, 1897 October 27; 4p.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
  - ANS to J. H. Johnston, 1898 January 25; postcard; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
  - ALS to Mr. Shanks, 1899 April 6; 3p.; Ingersoll, Robert Green, 1833-1899 (Box 3)
    About music.
  - ANS to George Clinton Genet, 1900 July 21; postcard; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
    Postcard about Conway's book on Paine.
  - ANS to J. H. Johnston, 1900 August 2; postcard; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907 (Box 3)
  - TLS to William Manley Van Der Weyde, 1870-1928, 1920 July 27; 1p.; Mayo, William James, 1861-1939 (Box 3)
    Response to Van Der Weyde's suggestion that Thomas Paine be inducted into the Hall of Fame.
  - TLS to William Manley Van Der Weyde, 1870-1928, 1921 November 16; 1p.; Edison, Thomas A., (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931 (Box 3)
    Edison agrees that "Paine was one of the greatest men of all time."
  - ALS to Dennis O'Bryen, Wednesday morning; 1p.; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835 (Box 3)
    About Cobbett's political plans.
  - ADS, n.d.; 2p.; Author unknown (Box 3)
    "certificat de residence du citoyen Louis Philippe noel Villant"
  - AD, n.d.; 3p.; Lacroze (Box 3)
    "Ratification" involving Jacques-Denis Goguet
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, n.d.; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 3)
  - AM, n.d.; 4p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "Anecdote of Thomas Paine"
  - AM, n.d.; 3p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "Extempore Preaching"
  - AM, n.d.; 2p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    The Model Republic, No 1.
  - AM, n.d.; 2p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "New York. Sixty one years ago..."
  - AM, n.d.; 6p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "A scrap from the Note Book of Laurie Todd, Importing Patriots, No 1"
  - AM, n.d.; 1p.; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "A scrap from the note book of Laurie Todd, Franklin"
  - AM, n.d.; 2 items (5p.); Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863 (Box 3)
    "The unholy Alliance of 1818, Count Mitternick, a Jesuite and villian..."